A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Program Files (Non-Grant), RG 5 FA1799
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Program-Related Files, 1975-2019; 6; 32.9 Cubic Feet 94 containers
  - Strategy and Assessment, 2005-2017; 13; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
    - Fund for Our Economic Future: Lessons Report, 2013 October (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 5431
      Two one page summaries about the strategic review undertaken to analyze the success of the Fund to transform the economy of Northeast Ohio.
    - Giving Day Playbook, 2013-2014 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 5432
      One page evaluation of KF campaign and copy of the Playbook, which was used to increase the effectiveness of community foundation online giving campaigns. Also included is "Ten Lessons From the KF Giving Day Initiative".
    - Growth in Foundation Support for Media in the U.S., 2013 November 12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 5430
      One page summary, one page evaluation and report commissioned by KF on media-related grantmaking by U.S. foundations.
    - New Americans Campaign: Interim Assessment, 2013 November 8 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 5433
      Assessment of the New Americans Campaign, a national initiative of funders, legal services providers and key institutions focused on increasing naturalization rates among eligible Legal Permanent Residents.
    - Narrowing Gaps, New Challenges, 2013 August (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 5444
      Summary and report re: efforts for Universal Access for all Americans.
    - Nonprofit News Sustainability Report, 2013 October 29 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 5434
      One page evaluation, summary and report re: comparative benchmarking study which examines 18 nonprofit news organizations and their progress toward sustainability (2010-2012).
    - Public Insight Network: Evaluation Update, c. 2013 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Knight File Number - 5435
      One page evaluation of the network of 8 newsrooms.
    - Role of News on Facebook, 2013 October 24 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Knight File Number - 5436
      One page evaluation and report on a survey of U.S. adults to better understand how Americans consume news on Facebook. The study was undertaken with the Pew Research Center.
    - University of Miami: Knight Center for International Media, c. 2013 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Knight File Number - 5437
      One page evaluation re: assessment of the overall performance of the Knight Center.
    - YouthBuild: Study on Pathways to Leadership, c. 2013 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Knight File Number - 5438
      One page evaluation and retrospective study on YouthBuild's alumni/ae to better understand the factors that initiate and sustain their civic engagement.
    - Arts & Culture Assessment for Summit County, 2014 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Knight File Number - 5439
      One page summary and retrospective study examines the arts and cultural sector serving Summit County from the many angles which impact its ability to serve the community as a whole.
    - Community and National Initiative Talent Research, 2014 May (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Knight File Number - 5440
      Powerpoint presentation of findings of the study: The Young and Restless in the Nation's Cities.
    - Knight Community Information Challenge, 2009-2013, 2014 January (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 5442
      Summaries for 2010, 2011, and 2012 and a report, "Reflections on KCIC from 2009-2013", prepared by FSG group.
    - Teach for America Interim Review, 2014 April 23 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 5446
      One page evaluation and report re: early results from an evaluation of TFA in Miami. The evaluation examines the impact of TFA's "clustering strategy" in Miami and explores the impact of TFA teachers versus non-TFA teachers.
    - (re) CONNECT: Advancing Opportunity, 2014 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 5453
      Report prepared by Hilary Hoeber is a "research snapshot" highlighting initial findings, framed in human-centered insights and opportunities, based on stories, quotes and conversations from Philadelphia and Oakland, CA.
    - Future of the First Amendment, 2014 August (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 5441
      Summary and report re: survey of high school students and teachers about first amendment rights.
    - Knight News Challenge 2010-11: What We Learned, 2014 August (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5443
      Summary and report that explores the innovations and impact of the KNC winners.
    - Decoding the Net Neutrality Debate, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5494
      Media, Public Comment and Advocacy on the Open Internet. This report, prepared by KF with Quid, a data analytics firm, analyzes the debate over net neutrality and provided information on media coverage, influencers, demographics, money spent and themes of public comments.
    - Magic of College Hill, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 5495
      How a university (Mercer) and a foundation (KF) turned around a depressed community by getting people to invest again. Report, authored by Dan Grech, also provides a statistical overview of the College Hill Revitalization. Also included is a Report to the Community, 2012-2014.
    - O, Miami: Reporter Analysis Series, c. 2014 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 5445
      One page evaluation and report re: O, Miami inaugural festival.
    - Gaining Ground: How nonprofit news ventures seek sustainability, 2015 April (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 5776
      Gaining Ground: This is the third installment in a series of reports produced by KF since 2011 to track the progress of nonprofit news sites as they strive for sustainability. The report analyses trends among 20 local, state and regional nonprofit news organizations. April 2015.
    - Mayoral Voting Reports, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 5567
      Two PowerPoint-type reports: "Who Votes for America's Mayors? A Pilot Study to Determine who Casts Ballots - and Who Doesn't - in 4 U.S. Cities: Charlotte, Detroit, Portland and St. Paul" and "Why Millennials Don't Vote For Mayor: Barriers and Motivators for Local Voting". The information was gathered by Lake Research Partners
    - Viewing The Future: Virtual reality in Journalism, 2016 May 13 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 5850
      Viewing The Future: Virtual reality in Journalism. Journalism underwent a flurry of virtual reality content, creation, production and distribution starting in the final months of 2015. Key findings: The state of virtual reality in journalism today.
    - Giving Day Initiative Summary Report, 2016 April 17 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 5894
      Giving Day Initiative Summary Report. KF launched a pilot program in 2012 to determine whether giving days would be an effective way for community foundations to experiment with technologies like online fundraising and social media. What began as a small pilot program evolved into a multi-faceted Giving Day Initiative, through which KF supported eighteen giving day organizers to run 25 giving days (draft report). Also included are notes on the Giving Day Initiative.
    - Lessons From the Early Years of Mission-Related Investing at Knight Foundation, 2016 May 10 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 5780
      Lessons From the Early Years of Mission-Related Investing at Knight Foundation. This report represents Knight's framework for understanding the social returns of the Knight Enterprise Fund, May 10, 2016.
    - Mobile-First News: How people use smartphones to access information, 2016 May (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 5781
      Mobile-First News: How people use smartphones to access information. This is a two-part series, excerpted from a custom research study conducted with Nielsen and commissioned by KF, delves first into several key findings, and then dives into how specific groups of people use different mobile platforms for news, May 2016.
    - Beyond the dollars: The long-term value of giving days for community foundations, 2016 August 10 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Knight File Number - 5889
      Beyond the dollars: The long-term value of giving days for community foundations. KF launched a pilot program in 2012 to determine whether giving days would be an effective way for community foundations to experiment with technologies like online fundraising and social media. This evaluation brought to light the numerous ways in which giving days provided long-term value to the community foundations that hosted them.
    - The Role of Human Relationship In Moving People to Action: The Messenger and the Medium Matter, 2016 October 27 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Knight File Number - 5848
      The Role of Human Relationship In Moving People to Action: The Messenger and the Medium Matter. A study conducted by 270 Strategies to show that people are more likely to respond to and engage with personalized content. They took this question of mobile messaging preferences to a community level.
    - Mobile News Notifications: A two-wave experiment with smartphone users, 2016 October 27 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Knight File Number - 5847
      Mobile News Notifications: A two-wave experiment with smartphone users. A study by the Engaging News Project at the University of Texas at Austin, examines the benefits of mobile push notifications to both drive traffic to journalistic content, and to inform the public.
    - Catalyzing Connections: The State of Miami's Startupt Ecosystem, c. 2016 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Knight File Number - 5778
      Catalyzing Connections: The State of Miami's Startup Ecosystem. This report takes an early look at the role and impact of Knight's investments in Miami's startup ecosystem. Engine Research Foundation compiled the findings in this report by analyzing secondary data sources and conducting individual interviews and surveys with grantees and other interested parties from the Miami community, March 22, 2016.
    - Excellence & Opportunities: A Research Study of the Miami Book Fair International, c. 2016 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Knight File Number - 5895
      The research study, conducted by Bendixen & Associates, was designed to engage and understand the perceptions of the wide variety of audiences important to the Miami Book Fair International and, by extension, of the Center for Writing and Literature at Miami Dade College.
    - From Airwaves to Earbuds, 2017 January 26 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 5845
      From Airwaves to Earbuds. Lessons from Knight Investments in digital audio and podcasting. Podcasting and on-demand audio is a rapidly evolving medium, ripe for experimentation and innovation.
    - OpenNews: Insights From Building A Community Of Newsroom Technologists, 2017 February (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 5884
      Opennews: Insights From Building A Community Of Newsroom. Knight commissioned an evaluation intended to assess both achievements and lessons to date and provide a framework for measuring network-related activities going forward. Key areas of inquiry included: Fellowship outcomes, Newsroom impact, Network effect. The evaluation was conducted from January 2016 to September 2016.
    - Changing Gears In the Motor City, 2017 April (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 5887
      Changing Gears In the Motor City: A Financial and Social Impact Assessment of the Detroit Development. This review examines the financial impact of the conversion to a grant in August 2015, as well as the Detroit Development Fund's broader social outcomes. Key Findings: Positive economic impact, Improved Financial Stability, Heightened Prospects for growth and gains in diversity with room for improvement.
    - Full Learning and Impact Research and Assessment Reports, 2017 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 5765
      An assessment of Knight Foundation's Local Media Initiative. KF commissioned Tim Griggs, a digital media consultant and former publisher of The Texas Tribune, to study the Local Media Initiative and decipher the status of local news organizations funded and broader lessons. The study examined grantee successes and challenges, promising models, critical needs across the local media space and ways that Knight and other funders could address those needs.
- Program-Related Investment Files, 2007-2014; 7; 2.28 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter boxes
  - Citizen Logistics, Inc., 2010-0282, 2010 December 1-2011 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5006
    Grant 20100282, Citizen Logistics, Inc., $150,000 to support the establishment of the Groundcrew Foundation and the preparation for the deployment of Groundcrew, a mobile-based tool for community organizing, at three nonprofit organizations in Silicon Valley.
  - Localocracy, 2011-0001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5515
    Grant 20110001, Localocracy, $100,000, to support an "Online Town Common" platform to enhance community dialogue in partnership with established media organizations.
  - Commons Labs, Inc., 2011-0204, 2011 September 2-2012 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5179
    Grant 20110204, Commons Labs, Inc., $222,000, to support the development of a digital platform for civic discourse.
  - Historic Macon Foundation, Inc., 2007-0030, 2007 March 12-2012 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5180
    Grant 20070030, Historic Macon Foundation, Inc., $700,000, to advance the revitalization of Macon's linchpin Beall's Hill neighborhood by creating a revolving loan fund and development incentive managed by the Historic Macon Foundation.
  - Independent Sector, 2011-0365, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5181
    Grant 20110365, Independent Center, $1,000,000, to help Independent Sector, one of the most important national support organizations to the field of philanthropy and nonprofits, recapitalize a real estate investment and focus on its core mission.
  - NowSpots, Inc., 2010-0143, 2010 June 14-2012 August 31 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5187
    Grant 20100143, NowSpots, Inc., $260,000, to develop open-source software allowing "real-time advertising" that can be updated at any time by local business using social media. Included in the PRI file is documentation on the proposed merger of NowSpots with Marin Software.
  - Participatory Cultural Foundation, 2011-0380, 2011 December 20-2012 December 31 (Box 2A, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5188
    Grant 20110380, Participatory Cultural Foundation, $250,000 to expand and improve the Universal Subtitles tool for titling and translating video across the Internet.
  - Stroome, 2010-0225, 2010 June 14-2012 August 31 (Box 2A, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5189
    Grant 20100225, Stroome, $230,000, to create a popular open source online collaborative video-editing platform.
  - Stroome, 2010-0225 (Box 2A, Folder 2)
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
  - Behavio, Inc., 2012-0165, 2012 July-2013 September (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5329
    Grant 20120165, Behavio, Inc., $200,000, to build an open source tool for collecting, analyzing, and making useful data collected from mobile devices.
  - Behavio, Inc., 2012-0165 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Common Place, 2012-0043, 2012 April-2013 March (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5333
    Grant 20120043, Common Place, $127,400, to build a web platform for local community engagement in Akron that uses trained community organizers and creates a local online sharing network for neighbors and civic leaders to connect.
  - Common Place, 2012-0043 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - NextDrop, 2011-0277, 2011 August-2013 July 31 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5514
    Grant 20110277, NextDrop, $375,000, to develop an open-source platform for using mobile phones and voice recognition to notify underserved community residents about the availability of water services.
  - Sirocco, 2012-0167, 2012 July-2013 October (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5513
    Grant 20120167, Sirocco $340,000 to develop a collaborative organizing dashboard for governments, outside organizations and the public to use in disaster response and other situations.
  - Daily Feats, 2012-0121, 2012 May-2014 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5516
    Grant 20120121, Daily Feats, $236,000, to increase community engagement feats completed by users of Daily Feats to 15 percent of the total actions on the platform and develop a statistical analysis of individuals' civic engagement interactions through social networks.
  - Daily Feats, 2012-0121 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Department of Better Technology, LLC, 2013-45680, 2013 October-2014 December (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5517
    Grant 2013-45680, The Department of Better Technology, LLC, $460,000. Without open, easy procurement government will consistently pay too much for the development and implementation of yesterday's technology. Because of this, returns on investment for open government are difficult to prove to the taxpayer. Procure.io is a proven system that makes procurement simpler and increases government's access to tech, driving down the cost of transparency and engagement.
  - ElectNext, 2012-0162, 2012 June-2014 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5518
    Grant 20120162, ElectNext, $150,000, to invest in the development and distribution of ElectNext, a voter education platform that matches voters to candidates, for down ballot races in Philadelphia.
  - ElectNext, 2012-0162 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Matter Ventures, 2011-0220, 2011 October-2014 October (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5519
    Grant 20110220, Matter Ventures, $2,500,000, to initiate and advise innovation in public media by establishing the Knight PRX Public Media Accelerator.
  - Miami Co Working LLC, 2012-0323, 2012 November-2014 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5520
    Grant 20120323, Miami Co Working LLC, $250,000, to strengthen Miami's startup community by creating a co-working facility for entrepreneurs to work, gather, share and learn.
  - NeighborGoods, 2012-0040, 2012 March 12-2014 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 5521
    Grant 20120040, NeighborGoods, $350,000, to partner with NeighborGoods and the City of San Jose to pilot an online tool that allows neighbors to engage offline by sharing goods and services with each other to strengthen social capital and trust.
  - NeighborGoods, 2012-0040 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Open Counter Enterprises, Inc., 2014-48095, 2013 June 21-2014 June 21 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 5522
    Grant 2014-48095, Open Counter Enterprises, Inc., $450,000. Open source software for governments to make it easier for residents to register and create new businesses.
  - Participatory Cultural Foundation, 2012-0347, 2012 December-2014 January 31 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 5523
    Grant 20120347, Participatory Cultural Foundation, $500,000, to put Amara, the collaborative tool for online video subtitling, onto a sustainable growth path through a program related investment.
  - SoChange, 2010-0186, 2010 September 9-2014 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 5524
    Grant 20100186, SoChange, $170,000, to create a software platform that aggregates consumer buying power and lets them direct it toward businesses that behave in socially responsible ways.
  - SoChange, 2010-0186 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - TKOH, 2012-0408, 2013 January-2014 January (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 5525
    Grant 20120408, TKOH, $330,000, for a tablet application that helps people easily record stories and oral histories, prompted by photos or videos on the screen.
  - TKOH, 2012-0408 (Box 6, Folder 1)